蜘蛛侠2
她每天都看着我
She looks at me every day.
玛莉珍·华森
Mary Jane Watson.
我真希望她知道  我有多爱她
Oh, boy. If she only knew how I felt about her.
但是我不能让她知道
But she can never know.
我选择为伸张正义奉献一生
I made a choice once to live a life of responsibility.
我不能让她陷入危险
A life she can never be a part of.
我是什么人
Who am I?
我是蜘蛛人  身负神圣使命
I'm Spider-Man, given a job to do.
我也是彼得·帕克  有一份伟大的工作
And I'm Peter Parker, and I, too, have a job.
帕克  帕克
Parker. Parker!
停  快停车
No, no, no, stop! Stop!
你迟到了  你老是迟到
Parker, you're late, man. Always late.
对不起  我被一件事耽搁了
I'm sorry, Mr. Aziz. There was a disturbance.
拜托  你每次都搞这种飞机
Another disturbance. Always a disturbance with you.
21分钟前有人叫了比萨
Come on, 21 minutes ago, in comes order.
浩然法律事务所  八个松厚饼皮什锦口味比萨
Harmattan, Burton & Smith. Eight extra-large deep-dish pizzas.
八分钟内不送到  就超过29分钟送达的保证
In eight minutes, I am defaulting on Joe's 29-minute guarantee.
这样一来  我不但收不到钱
Then, not only am I receiving no money for these pizzas...
连这个大客户都会被对手抢走
...but I will lose the cjustomer forever to Pizza Yurt.
我全靠你了  你要准时送到
Look, you are my only hope, all right? You have to make it in time.
你人很好  只是很不可靠
Peter, you're a nice guy. But you're just not dependable.
这是你最后一次机会
This is your last chance.
七分半钟内赶到那  不然我就炒你鱿鱼
You have to go 42 blocks in 7 1/2 minutes or your ass is fired.
快去啊
Go!
你猪头呀
Hey, what, are you stupid?
他抢了那家伙的比萨
Whoa! He stole that guy's pizzas!
我去捡
I'm gonna get it!
小朋友  别在大马路玩耍
Hey, you guys. No playing in the streets.
好  蜘蛛人哥哥
Yes, Mr. Spider-Man.
回头见
See you.
帅哟  蜘蛛人
Way to go, Spidey!
比萨送来了
Pizza time.
你迟到了
You're late.
我不会付钱
I'm not paying for those.
我保证29分钟内把比萨送达
Joe's 29-minute guarantee is a promise, man.
你不把这保证当回事  我却是很认真的
I know to you, Parker, a promise means nothing. But to me, it's serious.
我也很认真呀  老板
It's serious to me too, Mr. Aziz.
-你被开除了  走吧  -我需要这份工作
- You're fired. Go. - Please, I need this ob.
-你被开除了  -再给我一次机会
- You're fired. - Look, give me another chance.
你被开除了
You're fired.
-帕克  你被开除了  -为什么
- Parker, hello. You're fired. - Why?
接飞盘的小狗
Dogs catching Frisbees?
公园里的鸽子  两个下棋的老头
Pigeons in the park? A couple geezers playing chess?
-老板  -别烦我
- Boss. - Not now.
我只想呈现纽约市温馨的一面
The Bugle could show another side of New York for a change.
六分钟后截稿  缺头版版面
We got six minutes to deadline, Jonah. We need page one.
我付你钱不是让你搞艺术  我叫你别烦我
I don't pay you to be a sensitive artiste. I pay you... Still not now!
是因为蜘蛛人只肯让你拍照
I pay you because that psycho Spider-Man will pose for you.
他不肯让我拍照了  你害他成为全民公敌
He won't let me take any more pictures. You turned the whole city against him.
我可得意的咧
A fact I'm very proud of.
把这些恶心照片拿走  免得我把隔夜饭吐出来
Get your pretty little portfolio off my desk before I go into a diabetic coma.
-你太太说她把支票簿搞丢了  -这真是好消息
- It's your wife, she lost her checkbook. - Thanks for the good news.
你连一张都不肯采用吗  我真的很缺钱
Please, isn't there any of these shots you can use? I need the money.
布小姐  快拿纸巾来  让擦我眼泪
Miss Brant. Get me a violin.
只剩五分钟
Five minutes to deadline, Jonah.
登一张死鸡照片  头条是
Run a picture of a rancid chicken. Here's the headline:
禽流感侵袭纽约市
"Food Poisoning Scare Sweeps City."
-吃炸鸡都会中毒吗  -我不是说我快吐了吗
- Some food got poisoned? - I'm a little nauseous.
好吧  詹老板
All right, Mr. Jameson.
逊毙了  这就是头条新闻
It stinks. Robbie, there's your page one.
蒙面大坏蛋威胁纽约市
"Masked Menace Terrorizes Town."
他并不是大坏蛋
I told you, he's not a menace.
-我警告你  -我马上去办
- I told you... - I'll take care of it.
-我付你一百五十美元  -三百美元
- I'll give you 150. - Three hundred.
太贵了啦
That's outrageous.
好吧  拿去领钱
Done. Give this to the girl.
谢谢  再见
Thank you. Bye-bye.
嗨
Hi.
嗨  彼得
Hey, Pete.
这不够还你上次预支的钱
I don't think this covers the advance I gave you a couple weeks ago.
-对喔  -抱歉
- Right. - Sorry.
嘿
Hey.
抬起头来
Chin up, okay?
走路小心点
Watch it, jerk!
康博士  对不起
Dr. Connors. Sorry.
你要去哪儿
Where were you headed, Parker?
上你的课呀
To your class.
我的课上完了
My class is over.
你没看到我站在这儿吗
See me standing here?
对不起  我很努力想赶来
I'm sorry. I'm trying. I wanna be here.
那就要准时上课
Then be here.
看看你
Look at you, Peter.
你的成绩一落千丈  上课老是迟到
Your grades have been steadily declining. You're late for class.
你总是疲惫不堪
You always appear exhajusted.
你也还没交核融合的报告
Your paper on fusion is still overdue.
我计划写巴奥图博士的研究
I know. I'm planning to write it on Dr. Otto Octavius.
大学没有计划这门科系
Planning is not a major at this university.
巴博士是我的朋友
Octavius is a friend of mine.
你要好好写报告
Better do your research, Parker.
交不出来  我就会把你当掉
Get it done, or I'm failing you.
惊喜
Surprise!
说话呀
Well, say something.
今天是什么大日子
What's the occasion?
你忘啦  今天是你的生日
Oh,really, Peter. It's your birthday!
你看你自己都忘了
Whether you want to remember it or not.
他活在另一个世界  对吧  彼得
He lives in another reality. Don't you, Pete?
-嗨  玛莉珍  -嗨
- Hi, M.J. - Hi.
-好兄弟  -嗨
- Hey, buddy. - Hey.
好久不见
Long time, no see.
你演的舞台剧受到好评
So how's the play? I read a great review.
进行得挺顺利的
It's going fine. It's going good.
她演得超棒
She's brilliant in it.
哈利送我玫瑰花
Harry sent me roses.
你怎么都不回我电话
So where you been, pal? You don't return my calls.
我最近很忙
I've been busy.
忙着替蜘蛛人拍照  那只害虫近来好吗
Taking pictures of Spider-Man? How's the bug these days?
那个人你最好少见为妙
The less you see of that man, the better.
大家到餐厅吃饭吧
Now, let's all go into the other room and have something to eat.
我去拿点心
I'll get the hors d'oeuvres.
你在奥氏企业做得怎样
So how are things going at OSCORP?
很好  我现在是特别计划的总监
They're great. I'm head of Special Projects.
我们的核融合研究有重大突破
We're about to make a breakthrough on fusion.
你真能干  你父亲在天之灵一定以你为荣
How lovely, Harry. Your father would be so proud, rest his soul.
谢谢
Thank you.
我在资助你的偶像巴奥图博士
We're actually funding one of your idols, Pete. Otto Octavius.
-我正在写他的报告  -你想见他吗
- I'm writing a paper on him. - You want to meet him?
你肯带我去见他
You'd introduce me?
当然啰
You bet.
他会帮助奥氏企业达到
Octavius is gonna put OSCORP on the map...
连我爸也梦想不到的成就
...in a way my father never even dreamed of.
玛莉珍  过来帮忙
M.J., could you give me a hand?
她在等着你
She's waiting for you, pal.
什么意思
What do you mean?
她一直忍不住在偷瞄你
The way she looks at you or doesn't look at you.
难道你看不出来
However you want to look at it.
我现在没时间交女友
I don't have time for girls right now.
你是猪头吗
Why, are you dead?
我最近很忙
I've been kind of busy.
忙着替你朋友拍照
Taking pictures of your friend?
别再提了  好吗
Could we get off that subject?
我希望我们成为朋友  哈利  互相信任
I want us to be friends, Harry. I want us to trjust each other.
那就老实说
Then be honest with me.
你知道他是谁  会告诉我吗
If you knew who he was, would you tell me?
查封通知
梅
May.
班  什么事
Oh, what, Ben?
等一下
Wait.
-梅婶  -哎呀
- Aunt May. - Oh, my.
彼得  原来是你  我还以为我回到从前了
Oh, Peter. Oh, for a second there, I thought I was years ago.
大家都走了  对吧
Everybody's gone, aren't they?
他们开不开心
Did they have a good time?
很开心
I'm sure they did.
-你还好吧  -很好  你回去吧
- You okay? - Of course. But you go home.
小心点  骑摩托车很危险
And be careful. I don't like that scooter thing you drive around.
我很担心你
I'm worried about you.
你一个人孤零零的  我也看到银行寄来的信
You're so alone. And I saw the letter from the bank.
真是的  你看到了
Oh, my. You did?
别担心
Oh, well.
怎样呢
So?
我的经济状况不好
I'm a little behind.
大家都一样
Everybody is.
我不想再谈了
Anyway, I don't want to talk about it anymore.
我累了  你也该回家了
I'm tired, and you better start back home.
拿去  生日快乐
Here, kiddo. Happy birthday.
你比我更需要
You need it more than I do.
-我不能拿  -当然能
- No, I can't take that from you. - Yes, you can!
我给你就拿去
You can take this money from me.
这没多少钱  拿去吧
For God's sake, it's not much. Now, take it!
别偷偷留下来
And don't you dare leave it here.
对不起
Oh, I'm sorry.
我只是太想你的班叔叔
It's just that I miss your uncle Ben so much.
下个月就是他逝世两周年忌日
Can you believe that it's two years next month since he was taken?
我有时候会想
I think to myself at times...
如果我该为他的死负责
...were I to face the one responsible for what happened, I'd...
我真不知该如何是好
Oh, I don't know what I'd do.
来吧
Now...
把生日蛋糕带回去吃
...you better take the rest of your cake home.
嘿
Hey.
你还在这儿
Hey. You're still here.
我看到你的广告板
I saw your billboard on Bleecker.
很好笑吧  我有够丑了
Isn't it funny? I'm really kind of embarrassed.
一点也不会  我每天都能看到你真好
Don't be. It's nice. I get to see you every day now.
今天我见到你好开心
I liked seeing you tonight, Peter.
我也是
Oh, boy, yeah.
你也是什么
"Oh, boy, yeah" what?
没什么
Nothing.
你想对我说什么吗
Do you want to say something?
我
I...
我想问
...was...
你还住在东区吗
...wondering if you're still in the Village.
我真搞不懂你
You're such a mystery.
彼得
Peter.
什么
What?
生日快乐
Happy birthday.
我正与一个人见面
I'm seeing somebody now.
他是你男朋友吗
You mean, like a boyfriend?
我挺喜欢他的
Well, like I like him.
什么
What?
没什么
Nothing.
交男朋友很好呀
That's good, you know? Companionship...
-也许他不只是男朋友  -不只是
- May be more than that. - More?
我不晓得
I don't know.
我明晚会去看你的舞台剧
I'm coming to see your play tomorrow night.
-真的吗  -我一定会到
- You're coming? - I'll be there.
别让我失望
Don't disappoint me.
我不会的
I won't.
房租
Rent.
-嗨  -嗨你的头
- Hi. - Hi. What's "hi"?
我的房租咧
Can I spend it?
我这礼拜会领薪水
I have a paycheck due this week and...
-你的房租又迟交了一个月  -我保证
- You're a month late again. Again. - I promise as soon as...
如果保证能当饭吃  我女儿早就变成胖妹了
If promises were crackers, my daughter would be fat.
真的很抱歉  这是我这星期的生活费
I'm really sorry, Mr. Ditkovitch. All I got is this 20 for the rest of the week.
道歉也没用
"Sorry" doesn't pay the rent.
下次别溜进来  我的耳朵跟猫一样灵
And don't try to sneak past me. I have ears like a cat
眼睛跟老鼠一样尖
and eyes like a rodent.
-多谢了  房东先生  -嗨  彼得
- Thanks, Mr. Ditkovitch. - Hi, Pete.
有人吗
Hello?
房租咧
Rent?
博士  奥先生来了
Doctor? Mr. Osborn's here.
诺贝尔奖是你的囊中物  我们都会发大财
Nobel Prize, Otto. Nobel Prize. And we'll all be rich.
我不是为了得奖  哈利
It's not about the prizes, Harry.
但是你需要奥氏企业的资金
But you need money. You need OSCORP.
这位是谁
Who do we have here?
我跟你提过的超级天才
This is my good friend I called you about.
他帮我完成高中理工科
He got me through high-school science.
我是彼得·帕克  我正在写关于你的报告
Peter Parker, sir. I'm writing a paper on you for...
我知道你来的目的
I know what you're doing here...
可是我没空跟大学生闲扯
...but I don't have time to talk to students now.
不过奥氏企业是我的大金主
But OSCORP pays the bills, so...
没错  我得去参加董事会
That's why I have to take off. Board meeting.
你们这两个天才  就好好聊聊吧
But my job is done here. Got you two geniuses together.
祝明天好运  诺贝尔奖是你的  瑞典见
Good luck tomorrow, Otto. Nobel Prize. We'll see you in Sweden!
你朋友挺有意思的
Interesting fellow, your friend.
我不会占用你太多时间
I won't take much of your time.
我记得你是老康的学生  他说你头脑很好
Now I remember you. You're onnors' student. He tells me you're brilliant.
他也说你很懒惰
He also tells me you're lazy.
我一定会改进
I'm trying to do better.
头脑好还不够  你一定要努力向上
Being brilliant's not enough, young man. You have to work hard.
聪明不是特权  那是一种天赋
Intelligence is not a privilege, it's a gift.
你要用来造福人类
And you use it for the good of mankind.
就是这个吗
So. Is that it?
对  完成并维持核融合的机器
Yes. My design to initiate and sjustain fusion.
你使用原子的谐波频率
I understand you use harmonics of atomic frequencies.
其实是共振频率
Sympathetic frequencies.
借以加强核融合的效果
Harmonic reinforcement?
继续说
Go on.
最后产生出强大的能量
An exponential increase in energy output.
无穷无尽的能量
A huge amount of energy.
就像太阳一样  提供无穷无尽的能源
Like a perpetual sun providing renewable power for the whole world.
你能稳定核融合反应吗
Are you sure you could stabilize the fusion reaction?
我这一个半小时都在说什么
Peter, what have we been talking about for the last hour and a half?
这是我毕生的心血结晶
This is my life's work.
我知道计算错误的严重后果
I certainly know the consequences of the slightest miscalculation.
对不起  我不该质疑你
I'm sorry. I didn't mean to question you.
这位小朋友认为  我会把纽约炸掉
Rosie, our new friend thinks I'm gonna blow up the city.
你今晚可以高枕无忧
You can sleep soundly tonight.
他的研究无懈可击
Otto's done his homework.
明天来看测试  你就知道
Come to the demonstration tomorrow, and you'll see for yourself.
你倒是要好好睡一觉
And you need to sleep soundly tonight, Otto.
爱迪生发明电灯前有睡吗
Did Edison sleep before he turned on the light?
马可尼发明无线电前有睡吗
Did Marconi sleep before he turned on the radio?
贝多芬写第五交响曲前有睡吗
Did Beethoven sleep before he wrote the 5th?
伯努利在发明最小作用量原理前合过眼吗
Did Bernoulli sleep before he found the curves of quickest descent?
我很欣赏这个年轻人
RRRosie, I love this boy.
谈谈你自己  你有女朋友吗
Peter, tell us about yourself. Do you have a girlfriend?
这个嘛
Well...
我不知道耶
I don't really know.
你不是应该知道吗  你不知道谁知道
Well, shouldn't you know? I mean, who would know?
别逼他  也许这是秘密
Leave him alone. Maybe it's a secret love.
爱不应该是秘密
Love should never be a secret.
把爱这么复杂的事藏在心底
If you keep something as complicated as love stored up inside...
一定会把自己逼疯
...gonna make you sick.
我很幸运  能找到真爱
I finally got lucky in love.
我们都一样
We both did.
但绝非完美  爱要努力经营
But it's hardly perfect. You have to work at it.
我们同校  一开始我就知道会很辛苦
I met him on the college steps, and I knew it wasn't going to be easy.
他念理工  我念英国文学
He was studying science, and I was studying English literature.
我试着跟她解释相对论
That's right. I was trying to eplain the theory of relativity.
她试着跟我解释艾略特的诗
And RRosie was trying to explain T.S. Eliot.
我完全看不懂他在写什么
I still don't understand what he was talking about.
-你知道啦  -我是说真的
- Yes, you do. - I'm serious.
艾略特的诗比科学更深奥
T.S. Eliot is more complicated than advanced science.
不过你想追女孩  就读诗给她听
But if you want to get a woman to fall in love with you, feed her poetry.
读诗
Poetry.
屡试不爽
Never fails.
（自助洗衣店）
（朗费罗叶慈）
一个身材高挑修长的少女  独自站在草原上
A tall and slender maiden All alone upon a prairie
她身穿着翠绿色衣裳
Brightest green were all her garments
秀发有如阳光般闪亮
And her hair was like the sunshine
他日复一日凝视着她
Day by day he gazed upon her
（不可儿戏）
房租
Rent!
我的钱咧
Where is my money?!
你今晚好像很紧张
You seem jittery tonight.
你永远不知道什么人会来
You never know who's coming.
（康乃馨  三美元一束）
各位  五分钟后开演
Ladies, five minutes. Five minutes.
你怎么这么厉害
How'd you do that?
多运动、多休息
Work out, plenty of rest.
还有多吃青菜
You know, eat your green vegetables.
我妈也这么说  我以前都不信
That's what my mom is always saying. I just never actually believed her.
快点
Come on. Go.
稳着点
Keep it steady.
那是一张蜘蛛网
It's a web.
蜘蛛人  加油
Go, Spidey, go!
有麻烦了
We got trouble!
放我下来
Get me down!
我很相信孟先生说的话
I am more than content with what Mr. Moncrieff said.
光是听到他的声音  就令人放心
His voice alone inspires one with absolute credulity.
那我们该原谅他们吗
Then you think we should forgive them?
对
Yes.
我是说不对
I mean, no.
老兄  你违规停车会被拖吊
Hey. Hey. Hey, chief. You park there, I'm towing it.
随你便
Whatever.
鞋带松了
Shoelace.
领带也应该
You might want to...
-我能效劳吗  -我是来看戏的
- an I help you? - Yeah, I've come to see the show.
抱歉  开演后就不能进去
Oh, I'm sorry, sir. No one will be seated after the doors are closed.
这样才不会打扰到观众
It helps maintain the illusion.
华森小姐请我来看戏
Miss Watson, she's a friend of mine. She asked me to come.
但她没请你迟到
But not to come late.
我一定要进去  让我站在
I have to see this show. Just let me in, I'll stand in the...
（演出时  请保持安静）
蜘蛛人啊蜘蛛人
♪ A Spider-Man ♪
飞檐走壁、铲奸除恶
♪ A-does whatever a spider can ♪
吐出蜘蛛丝  织成蜘蛛网
♪ A-spins a web, any size ♪
坏人就像苍蝇自投罗网
♪ Catches thieves a-just like flies ♪
小心  蜘蛛人来了
♪ Look out ♪
♪ Here comes the Spider-Man ♪
今天你真的不一起来
You sure you don't wanna come tonight?
不了
Yeah, I'm sure.
-好吧  打电话给我  -好
- Okay. Call me. - I will.
-你今晚演得很棒  -谢谢
- You were great tonight. - Thanks.
大明星  请你帮我签名
May I have an autograph, please, miss?
你怎么会跑来
What are you doing here?
饿了吗
You hungry?
饿扁了
Starved.
是我  请在哔声后留言
Hi. It's me. Sing your song at the beep.
玛莉珍
Hi, M.J.
是我彼得
This is Peter.
昨晚我赶去看你的戏
I was on my way to your show and...
我骑着摩托车
Well, I was on my bike...
你在家吗
Are you there?
我真的计划了一整天
I really was planning on it all day.
但是
And...
我知道  你早料到我会让你失望
...I know you predicted I'd disappoint you.
那还用说
Bingo.
真是不可思议
It's amazing, isn't it?
我连八点准时到  这么简单的事
How complicated a simple thing...
都会把它搞得这么复杂
...like being someplace at 8:00 can become.
其实都怪那讨厌的影作员
Actually, there was this obnoxious usher.
应该有人去警告他
Somebody has to talk to that usher, M.J.
通话时间到了
Your time has expired.
请再投入五毛钱
Please deposit 50 cents for the next five minutes.
我很想告诉你实话
I wanna tell you the truth.
那就是
Here it is.
我是蜘蛛人
I'm Spider-Man.
奇怪吧
Weird, huh?
所以我不能跟你在一起
Now you know why I can't be with you.
如果我的敌人  知道你的存在
If my enemies found out about you...
而你因此受伤  我会永远自责
...if you got hurt, I could never forgive myself.
我真希望  能说出我对你的爱
I wish I could tell you how I feel about you.
各位先生  女士
Ladies and gentlemen...
我跟内人欢迎各位大驾光临
...my wife RRosie and I would like to welcome you this afternoon.
但是我要先问一声
But first, before we start...
谁丢了一捆用橡皮筋绑的钞票
...has anybody lost a large roll of 20-dollar bills in a rubber band?
我们只找到橡皮筋
Because we found the rubber band.
好冷的笑话
It's a terrible joke.
谢谢各位大驾光临
But thank you for coming.
今天
Today...
各位将目睹一种新能源的诞生
...you will witness the birth of a new fusion-based energy source.
一种安全永续性能源  为所有人提供廉价电力
Safe, renewable energy and cheap electricity for everyone.
我要介绍我的助手
And now let me introduce my assistants.
这四只机械手臂
These four actuators were developed and programmed...
是为了处理核融合而设计
...for the sole purpose of creating successful fusion.
它们能抗高温和磁力
They are impervious to heat and magnetism.
我的大脑透过神经连结  操控这些具有人工智慧的机械手臂
These smart arms are controlled by my brain through a neural link.
纳米神经导线  直接传递指令
Nanowires feed directly into my cerebellum...
让我在极度危险的环境
...allowing me to use these arms to control fusion reaction...
使用机械手臂  控制核融合反应
...in an environment no human hand could enter.
这些机械手臂具有
Doctor, if the artificial intelligence in the arms...
这么先进的人工智慧
...is as advanced as you suggest...
你不会反被它们控制吗
...couldn't that make you vulnerable to them?
问得好
How right you are.
所以我研发了一枚抑制晶片
Which is why I developed this inhibitor chip...
保护我的大脑功能
...to protect my higher brain function.
让我左右这些机械手臂的行动  而不是被它控制
It means I maintain control of these arms, instead of them controlling me.
压轴好戏开始了
And now on to the main event.
请打蓝灯
Give me the blue light, RRosie.
最重要的关键是  稀有的氚元素
Precious tritium is the fuel that makes this project go.
全地球只有25磅的存量
There's only 25 pounds of it on the whole planet.
我要感谢奥哈利的大力赞助
I'd like to thank Harry Osborn and OSCORP Indjustries for providing it.
我很乐意替你付帐单
Happy to pay the bills, Otto.
各位先生女士
Ladies and gentlemen...
系好安全带
...fasten your seat belts.
成功达到核融合反应
Doctor, we have a successful fusion reaction.
这是令尊梦想不到的非凡成就
This is a breakthrough beyond your father's dreams.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们达到一百亿瓦的发电量
We're producing a thousand-megawatt surplus.
太阳的能量
The power of the sun...
就在我的手掌心
...in the palm of my hand.
别惊慌  这只是跳电
Keep calm! It's only a spike!
很快就会稳定
It'll soon stabilize!
各位  请尽快离开
Ladies and gentlemen, please clear the room.
（警报  系统负荷过量）
防护罩破裂
We have a containment breach!
奥图  快回来
Otto, please get back!
快关掉  快关掉
Shut it off, Otto! Shut it off!
它会稳定  我能控制它
It will stabilize! It's under control!
这儿我作主
I'm in charge here!
我出的钱  我作主
It's my money! I'm in con...
我还是不原谅你
This doesn't change anything.
-你在干嘛  -关掉电源
- What are you doing? - Pulling the plug.
不
No!
萝丝
Rosie!
小心
Watch it.
差点就酿成大祸
That was too close.
用超过一滴氚元素  纽约就毁了
If he had more than a drop of tritium, he could have destroyed the city.
这下我毁了
I'm ruined.
我要跟蜘蛛人算这笔帐
I have nothing left, except Spider-Man.
他救了你一命
He saved your life, sir.
我才不屑他来救我
He humiliated me by touching me.
记者马上赶到  快走吧
The press will be here soon. I suggest we move on.
他跑来干嘛
What was he doing here anyway?
熔铁贯穿他的脊髓腔
Molten metal penetrated the spinal cavity...
脊椎多处受损
...and fused the vertebrae at multiple points...
包括脊椎板和脊柱
...including the lamina and the roof of the spinal column.
一定要开刀  才能进行诊断
We won't know the extent of the damage until we get in there.
我们要锯断这些机械手臂
I suggest we cut off these mechanical arms, slice up the harness...
有必要的话  必须切除脊椎板
...and, if need be, consider a laminectomy...
并进行后侧脊椎融合固定
...with posterior spinal fusion from C7-T1 to T12.
准备好了
We're ready, doctor.
有人锯过木头吗
Anybody here take shop class?
不  不  不
No! No! No!
救救我
Help me! Help me!
不
No!
消息传开来了  到处都有谣言跟八卦
It's all over town, Robbie. Gossip. Rumors.
幸运的话  会引起全城恐慌
Panic in the streets, if we're lucky.
疯狂科学家变成怪物
Crazy scientist turns himself into some kind of a monster.
他的身上装了四只机械手臂
Four mechanical arms welded right onto his body.
姓巴的家伙变成八手怪  太玄乎了
Guy named Otto Octavius winds up with eight limbs. What are the odds?
小何
Hoffman!
这怪物要叫什么
What are we gonna call this guy?
-八爪博士  -烂名字
- "Dr. Octopus." - That's crap.
-章鱼科学家  -逊毙了
- "Science Squid"? - Rap!
-怪异博士  -这名字挺炫的
- "Dr. Strange." - That's pretty good.
可惜有人用了  有了  八爪博士
But it's taken. Wait, wait! I got it. "Dr. Octopus."
-可是  超炫的  -当然啰
- I like it. - Of course you do.
八爪博士  全新的大坏蛋八爪博士
Dr. Octopus. New villain in town. "Doc Ock."
-你真是天才  -你等着加薪吗
- Genius. - What, are you looking for a raise?
快滚吧
Get out.
老板  我找到帕克了
Chief, I found Parker.
你死到哪儿  没缴电话费吗
Where you been? Why don't you pay your phone bill.
你没拍到疯狂科学家的照片
Mad scientist goes berserk, we don't have pictures!
我听说蜘蛛人也在场
I heard Spider-Man was there.
难不成你跑去拍松鼠吗  你被开除了
Where were you? Photographing squirrels? You're fired.
今晚的天文馆派对
Chief, the planetarium party.
你没被开除  我需要你
You're un-fired. I need you, come here.
你对上流社会了解多少
What do you know about high society?
-嗯  我  -你不用回答
- Oh. Well, l... - Don't answer that.
原来的摄影师被马球K到  我只有你了
My society photographer got hit in the head by a polo ball. You're all I got.
为美国英雄举行庆功宴  我儿子是太空人
Big party for an American hero. My son, the astronaut.
你能预支我薪水吗
Ould you pay me in advance?
你是说真的  我付你钱傻傻地站着吗
You serious? Pay you for what? Standing there?
明晚八点整  快滚吧
The planetarium, tomorrow night, 8:00. There's the door.
我心爱的萝丝死了
My Rosie's dead.
我的梦想破灭
My dream is dead.
这些
And these...
可怕的东西  应该沉下去
...monstrous things should be at the bottom of the river...
连我一起葬身河底
...along with me.
我的脑里
Something...
有一个声音
...in my head.
它在说话
Something talking.
抑制晶片
The inhibitor chip!
不见了
Gone.
重头来过
Rebuild.
不行
No.
彼得说的对
Peter was right.
我算错了
I miscalculated.
我不可能算错
I couldn't have miscalculated.
核融合不是成功了吗
It was working, wasn't it?
对
Yes.
我们重头来过  加大防护罩
We could rebuild. Enlarge the containment field.
让它比上一次更大更强
Make it bigger and stronger than ever.
但是我们需要钱
But we need money.
去抢银行
Steal it?
不行  我不能犯罪
No, no, no, I'm not a criminal.
没错
That's right.
不完成我的梦想  才是罪恶
The real crime would be not to finish what we started.
就在这里完成
We'll do it here.
太阳能量  就在我的手掌心
The power of the sun in the palm of my hand.
没有人能阻挡我们
Nothing will stand in our way.
没有人
Nothing!
（贷款部）
-这是我的社会保险  -我看到了
- That's the social security. - Yes, I see.
这是我班叔叔的寿险
My uncle Ben's life insurance.
是的  但是很抱歉
Yes, but I'm afraid...
这还是不够让你们重新贷款
...it's just not sufficient to refinance your home.
我又开始教钢琴了
Oh, but I'm giving piano lessons again.
真的吗
You are?
谢谢你在本银行
We appreciate that you've just opened up...
开了一个超省钱帐户
...a new supersaver account with us today.
但是
But the fact is...
你的资产不足以重新贷款  很抱歉
...you do not have the assets to justify this loan. I'm sorry.
这个嘛
Well...
我至少能拿到烤面包机
At least we get the toaster.
存款要超过三百元  才有得拿
Actually, that's only with a deposit of 300 or more.
我明白了
Oh, yes, I see.
好吧
Okay.
别担心  一定会有办法
Don't worry, we'll figure it out.
彼得
Peter?
别把我丢下来
Don't leave me.
这孩子真是个大英雄
Oh, that boy of yours is a real hero.
不准动
Hold it!
把手举起来  全都举起来
Put your arms up! All of them!
这是找你的零钱
Here's your change!
惨了  拜托
Oh, no. Come on!
-你把我给惹毛了  -我专门抓坏蛋
- You're getting on my nerves. - I have a knack for that.
你死定了
Not anymore.
-不准动  -站住
- Freeze! Don't move! - Freeze!
-别开枪  -别跟来
- Hold your fire! - Don't follow me.
等一下
Wait a second.
-把她交给我  -没问题
- Hand her over. - Of course.
慢慢来
Easy, now.
我真是不小心
Butterfingers.
小心
Look out!
救命
Help me!
-救救我  -我来了
- Help me! - I'm coming!
抓紧了
Hang on!
救命啊
Help!
谢谢
Thank you.
梅婶
Aunt May.
你未免也太多管闲事了
You've stuck your webs in my business for the last time.
这老太婆的命  要算在你头上
Now you'll have this woman's death on your conscience.
来呀
Come on.
你真不要脸
Shame on you.
你没事了
There you go.
谢谢你  我以前错怪你了
Thank you. Oh, have I been wrong about you.
我们把他打败了
We sure showed him.
是我把他打败的吧
What do you mean, "we"?
带我走  蜘蛛人
- Take me with you, Spider-Man. - Take me.
-来拍一张吧  -好  拍吧
- May I? - Sure. Go ahead.
潘妮  过来
Penny! Over here!
别拿走
Leave it.
你别喝这么多
Hey. Might wanna take it easy, buddy.
何不呢  这不是个派对吗
Why? It's a party.
我以为  那疯子会让我名利双收
Wouldn't you be drinking if you lost a bundle on some crackpot...
结果却被他弄得身败名裂
...who you thought was gonna take you with him to fame and fortune?
还有那只大昆虫
Not to mention your friend the bug.
今晚别提他
Not tonight, Harry.
我每晚都要说  我无论如何都要找到他
Every night! Until I find him, it's 24-7.
帕克
Parker!
你聋啦  我叫了你两次
Parker! What, are you deaf? I called you twice.
我是请你来喝香槟吗
Think I'm paying you to sip champagne?
替我老婆跟部长拍一张
Get a shot of my wife with the minister.
好帅的领带
Beautiful tie.
替我们跟检察官拍一张
Get a shot of us with the DA.
好美的礼服
Beautiful dress.
替市长跟他的二奶拍一张
Here, get a shot of the mayor and his girlfriend.
我是说老婆啦
Wife.
各位先生女士  晚安
Ladies and gentlemen, good evening.
纽约科学图书馆协会
The committee for the Science Library of New York...
很荣幸介绍今晚的贵宾
...is pleased to present our guest of honor.
他是第一个在月球踢足球的人
He's the first man to play football on the moon.
英俊勇敢  秀色可餐的
The handsome, the heroic, the delicious...
詹约翰上尉
...Captain John Jameson.
嗨
Hi.
-是你  -对不起
- You. - Listen, I'm sorry.
那天我有事耽搁了
But there was a disturbance.
我已经不认识你了
I don't know you.
我不能老是对你念念不忘  这太痛苦了
And I can't keep thinking about you. It's too painful.
我最近在读诗
I've been reading poetry lately.
随你便啦
Whatever that means.
他日复一日凝视着她
Day by day he gazed upon her
他日复一日为爱叹息
Day by day he sighed with passion Day by day...
省省吧你
Don't start.
我替你拿杯酒
An I get you a drink?
我是约翰的女友  他会为我服务
I'm with John. He'll get me my drink.
约翰
John.
约翰看过我的戏五次
By the way, John has seen my show five times.
哈利看过两次  梅婶看过一次
Harry has seen it twice. Aunt May has seen it.
我病重的老妈也来看过
My sick mother got out of bed to see it.
就连我那死鬼老爸
Even my father.
都跑到后台向我借钱
He came backstage to borrow cash.
但一向最关心我的好友
But my best friend, who cares so much about me...
却一次也没来过
...can't make an 8:00 curtain.
过了这么多年
After all these years...
对我来说  他竟是一张空座位
...he's nothing to me but an empty seat.
我对你很不爽  你为了蜘蛛人背叛好朋友
It pisses me off, your loyalty to Spider-Man and not to your best friend.
他杀死我父亲  你却为了靠他赚钱  替他辩解
I find him with my father's body, and you defend him.
-冷静点  -别推我
- Take it easy. - Don't push me.
别假装你是我朋友
Don't act like you're my friend.
你从我手上抢走玛莉
You stole M.J. From me.
你也抢走我的父爱
You stole my father's love.
你不肯交出蜘蛛人把我爸害死
Then you let him die because you didn't turn in the freak. Isn't that right?
对不对  是不是这样
Huh? Isn't that right?
好兄弟
Huh, brother?
各位  我要宣布一个好消息
Ladies and gentlemen, I just want you all to know...
美丽的玛莉珍刚答应我的求婚
...that the beautiful Miss Mary Jane Watson has just agreed to marry me.
太让人惊讶了
What a surprise.
别发呆  快拍照
Parker, wake up! Wake up! Shoot the picture!
不  惨了
Oh, no. No!
我怎么会这么衰
Why is this happening to me?
蜘蛛人和八爪博士狼狈为奸
你没什么毛病
You seem very okay to me.
我认为
My diagnosis?
这是心理问题
It's up here.
你说你睡不着  你为了什么伤心或做噩梦吗
You say you can't sleep. Heartbreak? Bad dreams?
我做了一个梦
There is one dream where...
在这个梦中
...in my dream...
我是蜘蛛人
...I'm Spider-Man.
但我失去了超能力  我想飞檐走壁  却一直摔下来
But I'm losing my powers. I'm climbing a wall, but I keep falling.
你是蜘蛛人
So you're Spider-Man.
只有在我的梦中
In my dream.
其实也不是我做的梦  是我朋友做的梦
Actually, it's not even my dream. It's a friend of mine's dream.
所以这是别人的梦
So it's somebody else's dream.
你的这位朋友
What about this friend?
他为什么要飞檐走壁  他觉得自己是什么
Why does he climb these walls? What does he think of himself?
这就是他的问题  他不知道自己是什么
That's the problem. He doesn't know what to think.
当你不了解自己一定会发疯  灵魂会消失
Gotta make you mad not to know who you are. Your soul disappears.
这种自我否定最可怕
Nothing as bad as uncertainty.
听好
Listen...
也许你不该当飞檐走壁的蜘蛛人
...maybe you're not supposed to be Spider-Man climbing those walls.
所以你才会一直摔到地面
That's why you keep falling.
你有选择的余地
You always have a choice, Peter.
我是有所选择
I have a choice.
你最近的这些念头
All the things you've been thinking about, Peter...
让我很伤心
...make me sad.
难道你不明白吗
Can't you understand?
我深爱玛莉珍
I'm in love with Mary Jane.
我以前教你要见义勇为
Peter, all the times we've talked of honesty...
铲奸除恶  伸张正义
...fairness, justice...
我一直都希望你能鼓起勇气
Out of those times, I counted on you to have the courage...
把我的梦想发扬光大
...to take those dreams out into the world.
我不能活在你的梦想中
I can't live your dreams anymore.
我要属于自己的人生
I want a life of my own.
你拥有一个天赋
You've been given a gift, Peter.
能力愈强  责任愈大
With great power comes great responsibility.
孩子  握我的手
Take my hand, son.
不  班叔叔
No, Uncle Ben.
我只是彼得·帕克
I'm just Peter Parker.
我不再是
I'm Spider-Man...
蜘蛛人
...no more.
再也不是了
No more.
-臭小子  -对不起
- You punk! - Sorry.
-谢了  -不客气
- Thanks. - You're welcome.
快点
Hurry up!
当零界是中子等于零  那么本正值是多少
And when the borderline is tau equals zero, the eigenvalues are?
有人知道吗
Someone, please?
0.23电子伏特
.23 electron volts.
你表现得很好  加油
Excellent work today, Parker. Keep it up.
其实我人并不坏  千万别把我当坏人
I'm not really wicked at all. You mustn't think that I'm wicked.
如果是这样  你就是在骗我们
If you are not, then you have certainly been deceiving us all...
这种行为不可原谅
...in a very inexcusable manner.
我希望你不是双面人
I hope you have not been leading a double life...
表面上耍坏  内心其实很善良
...pretending to be wicked and being really good all the time.
这样就很伪善
That would be hypocrisy.
我以前是有点坏
Of course, I have been rather reckless.
我很高兴
"I am glad."
我这么说你不高兴吗
Are you glad to hear it?
我很高兴
I am glad...
你这么说
...to hear it.
不过我得承认
In fact, now you mention the subject...
我是有点坏
...I have been very bad in my own small way.
你演得好棒  这出戏超好看
You were so wonderful. That was such a great play.
你应该跟我说你要来
You could've told me you were coming.
我怕你叫我不要来
I was afraid you'd say, "Don't come."
你看起来不太一样
You look different.
我擦了鞋  烫了裤子  做了功课
I shined my shoes, pressed my pants, did my homework.
我现在都会做功课
I do my homework now.
你想吃炒面吗
You wanna get some chow mein?
彼得
Peter...
我要结婚了
...I'm getting married.
我一直想像你会在山坡上结婚
I always imagined you getting married on a hilltop.
新郎是谁
And who's the groom?
你还没决定
You hadn't decided yet.
你以为来看戏
You think just because you saw my play...
就能阻止我结婚
...you can talk me out of getting married?
你说过你爱我  我以前不知好歹
You once told me you loved me. I let things get in the way before.
我以为一定要做一件事  现在不必做了
There was something I thought I had to do. I don't have to.
来不及了
You're too late.
请你考虑一下
Will you think about it?
考虑什么
Think about what?
让我们重头来过
Picking up where we left off.
重头来过
Where was that?
从来没开始怎么能重头来过
We never got on. You can't get off if you don't get on.
我认为事情没这么简单
I don't think it's that simple.
当然了  你老把事情搞得很复杂
Of course you don't, because you complicate things.
你不明白
You don't understand.
我不再是个空座位
I'm not an empty seat anymore.
我跟以前不同
I'm different.
打我一拳我会痛
Punch me, I bleed.
我得走了
I have to go.
我要在教堂结婚
I'm getting married in a church.
你是跟以前不一样
You are different.
（八爪博士逍遥法外）
这是场婚礼  别把我搞到破产
Dear, we agreed to put on a wedding, not go into bankruptcy.
鱼子酱  你邀请沙皇吗
Caviar? What, are we inviting the czar?
弄点饼干和烤香肠就行了
Get some cheese and crackers, some of those little cocktail weenies.
清洁队员找到一样好东西
I got a garbage man here says he's got something you might want to see.
如果你找到ET  有人已经捷足先登了
If you have an extraterrestrial's head in there, you're the third guy this week.
你在哪儿找到的
Where the hell did you get that?
垃圾桶
In the garbage.
In the garbage?
他一定是不干了
He must've given up.
举白旗投降了  不玩这个无聊游戏了
Thrown in the towel. Abandoned his sad little masquerade.
我终于把他整垮了  这是狗仔队的大胜利
I finally got to him. The power of the press triumphs.
你说是就是  我总有钱拿吧
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Now, look, I think I deserve a little something for this.
-我给你五十块  -我不如上网站拍卖
- Give you 50 bucks. - I could get more than that on eBay.
好吧  一百块钱  顺便给他一块香皂
All right, 100. Give this man his money and throw in a bar of soap.
老板娘还在线上
Your wife is still on that line.
鲜花  多少
Flowers? How much?
你干脆拿花到我坟上上香吧
You spend any more on this thing, you can pick the daisies off my grave.
用塑胶花
Get plastic.
有大新闻  我要挂了
Gotta go, big story.
（蜘蛛人玩完了）
蜘蛛人啊蜘蛛人
Spider-Man Spider-Man
你到哪儿去了
Where have you gone to Spider-Man?
快  抢他的钱
Come on, man. Get the money.
快点啦
Come on, come on.
救命啊
Help!
快点
Come on!
（挚爱的丈夫和叔叔  班帕克）
他死得好冤枉
It wasn't fair to have gone like that.
他是个好人
He was a peaceful man.
这都是我的错
And it was all my doing.
梅婶  你不该责怪自己
Aunt May. You don't have to punish yourself.
我知道
Oh, I know I shouldn't.
只是那天你要搭地铁
It's just that you wanted to take the subway...
他却要开车送你
...and he wanted to drive you.
如果我坚持不让他去
If only I had stopped him.
我们就能一起喝茶聊天
We'd all three of us be having tea together.
这是我的错
I'm responsible.
什么事
For what?
我应该对他的死负责
For what happened to Uncle Ben.
你那天在图书馆
But you were at the library.
做功课
You were doing your homework.
他送我到门口  可是我没进去
He drove me to the library, but I never went in.
什么意思
What do you mean?
我去了别的地方
I went someplace else.
我想赢些钱
Someplace where I thought I could win some money...
用来买辆车
...to buy a car, because I wanted...
我想用来追玛莉珍
...to impress Mary Jane.
事情发生得太快
It happened so fast.
我赢了钱可是对方不付钱  后来他遇到抢匪
I won the money, and the guy wouldn't pay me. Then he got robbed.
那个抢匪
The thief...
朝着我跑来
...was running towards me.
我大可以拦住他
I could've stopped him, but I wanted...
可是我想报仇
...revenge.
我让他逃走
I let him go.
I let him get away.
他需要一辆车
He wanted a car.
他想抢班叔叔的车
He tried to take Uncle Ben's.
班叔叔不肯
Uncle Ben said no...
所以就被他开枪打死
...and then he shot him.
班叔叔不肯向恶势力低头
Uncle Ben was killed that night...
那晚才会死在坏人枪下
...for being the only one who did the right thing.
而我
And I...
我只能在他死前
I held his hand...
握住他的手
...when he died.
我一直想告诉你
I've tried to tell you so many times.
我还得做一件事
Just one more little chore.
（蜘蛛人涉嫌杀死奥斯朋）
（蜘蛛人动用私刑）
你在哪儿
Where are you?
-少爷  我要走了  -你走吧
- I'm leaving for the night, sir. - Fine.
老爷只为工作发狂
Your father only obsessed over his work.
晚安  伯纳
Good night, Bernard.
你好  哈利
Hello, Harry.
奥图  你要什么
Otto. What do you want?
珍贵的氚元素
That precious tritium.
这次我要更多
But I need more of it this time.
你疯啦  你会把纽约市给毁了  你这二流科学家
More tritium, are you crazy? You'll destroy the city! You're a hack!
喂
Hey! Hey!
住手  好啦
Stop! Stop! All right!
好啦  好啦  放我下来  我们谈个条件
All right, all right, all right. Put me down. We'll make a deal.
你杀了蜘蛛人我就把东西给你
Kill Spider-Man, I'll give you all the tritium you need.
我改变主意  我要你活捉他
On second thought, bring him to me alive.
我该怎么找到他
How do I find him?
-彼得·帕克  -帕克
- Peter Parker. - Parker?
他替报社拍蜘蛛人的照片
He takes pictures of Spider-Man for the Bugle.
逼他说出他的下落
Make him tell you where he is.
把东西准备好
Have it ready.
别伤害彼得
Don't hurt Peter!
（犯罪率上升75%  蜘蛛人在哪里）
救人啊
Somebody, help!
起火了
Fire!
老陈找不到他女儿  你有没有看到她
Alisa, the hens can't find their daughter. Have you seen her?
快通知消防队  快呀
Somebody call the fire department! Help!
-救人啊  -有人被困在里面
- Help! - Is anybody in that building?
二楼有个小女孩
We think there's a kid stuck on the second floor.
你要去哪儿
Hey, where you going?!
我来了
I'm coming!
没事了  我会救你出去
It's okay. It's okay. Come here. I'm gonna get you out of here.
来吧  来吧
Come on. Come on.
妈妈
Mama.
小子  你真带种
You got some guts, kid.
有人被困在四楼  没逃出来
Some poor soul got trapped on the fourth floor. Never made it out.
天啊
Oh, man.
把东西收一收  走吧
All right, Billy, let's knock it down and roll them up. Get on out of here.
收工了  我们走吧
Let's pick it up! Let's get all this equipment, let's go! Let's move it!
难道我不该得到我要的爱
Am I not supposed to have what I want?
过我想过的生活吗
What I need?
我该怎么做
What am I supposed to do?
我不该没敲门
I shouldn't have without...
就闯进来
...knocking.
请进
Come in.
-嗨  -嗨
- Hi. - Hi.
你想吃巧克力蛋糕吗
Would you like a piece of chocolate cake?
好吧
Okay.
还有一杯牛奶
And a glass of milk?
这样很好
That would be nice.
好吧
Okay.
谢谢
Thank you.
有人留言给你
You got a message.
是你的婶婶
It's your aunt.
谢了
Thanks.
这是怎么回事
What's going on?
他们宽限我几个礼拜  不过我决定现在就搬家
Oh, they gave me another few weeks, but I decided the hell with it.
我找到一间小公寓
I'm moving on. I found a small apartment.
你怎么不告诉我
Why didn't you tell me?
我可以自己照顾自己
I'm quite able to take care of things myself.
对面的亨利来帮忙
And Henry Jackson across the street is giving me a hand...
我付他五块钱
...and I'm giving him $5.
那是亨利杰克森
That's Henry Jackson?
才过了两年  他就长这么大
Yes. It's funny what happens in two years.
他年纪小  志气却很大
Nine years old, has great ambitions.
关于上次那件事
Listen, about my last visit...
够了  别再说了
Pish-posh, we needn't talk about it.
过去的事  就让它过去吧
It's water over the dam or under the bridge or wherever you like it.
你能说实话  真的很勇敢
But you made a brave move in telling me the truth.
我以你为荣
And I'm proud of you.
我要谢谢你
And I thank you, and I...
我很爱你  彼得
I love you, Peter.
很爱很爱你
So very, very much.
我的漫画呢
Hey. Where are all my comic books?
那堆垃圾  我都拿去送人了
Those dreadful things? I gave those away.
-我把锅子装好了  -谢谢你
- I put the pans in the box, Mrs. Parker. - Thank you, Henry.
-嗨  彼得  -嗨  亨利
- Hi, Peter. - Hey, Henry.
你长好高
You're getting tall.
请你把食谱跟厨具装在一起
Henry, why don't you put those cookbooks in with the mixer.
你专门替蜘蛛人拍照
Okay. You take Spider-Man's pictures, right?
那是以前
I used to.
他人呢
Where is he?
最近  报上都没有他的照片
Henry and I agree. We don't see his picture in the paper anymore.
他
He...
-洗手不干了  -为什么
...quit. - Why?
他想做别的事
Wanted to try other things.
他会回来  对吧
He'll be back, right?
我不晓得
I don't know.
你猜不到他想当谁
You'll never guess who he wants to be.
蜘蛛人
Spider-Man.
-为什么  -他看得出谁是英雄
- Why? - He knows a hero when he sees one.
很少人像他一样飞檐走壁
Too few characters out there, flying around like that...
冒险救我这种老太婆
...saving old girls like me.
像亨利这种小孩子需要英雄
And Lord knows, kids like Henry need a hero.
牺牲小我完成大我的英雄
Courageous, self-sacrificing people...
当我们的好榜样
...setting examples for all of us.
每个人都喜欢英雄
Everybody loves a hero.
大家会替他们加油打气
People line up for them. Cheer them. Scream their names.
他们也会在雨中守候多时
And years later, they'll tell how they stood in the rain for hours...
只为了看一眼
...just to get a glimpse of the one...
当初拼命救他们一命的英雄
...who taught them to hold on a second longer.
我相信  每个人都拥有英雄本质
I believe there's a hero in all of us...
它让我们忠于自我
...that keeps us honest...
给我们力量
...gives us strength...
让我们拥有高贵情操
...makes us noble...
最后让我们光荣地死去
...and finally allows us to die with pride.
虽然有时候必须牺牲小我
Even though sometimes we have to be steady...
放弃我们最珍爱的东西
...and give up the thing we want the most.
甚至我们的梦想
Even our dreams.
蜘蛛人启发了亨利
Spider-Man did that for Henry...
他想知道他去了哪里
...and he wonders where he's gone.
他需要他
He needs him.
替我把书桌抬进车库  好吗
Do you think you could lift that desk and put it into the garage for me?
不要太勉强哦
But don't strain yourself.
好吧
Okay.
专心去想我要什么
Strong focus on what I want.
我回来了
I'm back!
我的背
My back.
你确定不邀请你的摄影师朋友
Honey, you sure you don't want to invite your friend, the photographer?
彼得·帕克
Peter Parker?
确定
Positive.
我以为他是你的好友
Thought he was your pal.
-彼得·帕克  -是啊
- Peter Parker? - Yeah.
他只是个大烂人
He's just a great big jerk.
世上有太多大烂人
The world's full of great big jerks.
你是大好人
You're adorable.
我只是穿了帅气制服
It's just the uniform.
把头往后仰
Lean your head back for me.
-往后仰  -快点啦
- Put my head back? - Yeah, just do it.
只要把头往后仰
Just put my head back?
好吧
Okay.
哇
Wow.
我又飞到月球上了
I'm back on the moon.
你也跟我一样吗
You up there with me?
-你好  -你吓了一跳吧
- Hiya. - Surprised?
吓了一大跳
Very.
谢谢你赶来
Thanks for coming.
一切都还好吧
Everything okay?
可以这么说
You might say so.
真好笑  我不知该从何说起
This is funny. I'm not sure how to begin.
你知道人有时候都会自欺欺人
You know how our minds play tricks on us.
-我也是  -我就是最好的例子
- Tell me about it. - Well, mine did a real number on me.
那晚我听到你对我的告白
Some part of me heard what you had to say after the show that night...
你说你为我改变了  只是我听不进去
...that you were different. But I didn't want to listen.
我不敢相信你
I was afraid to trust you.
但是我最近想了很多
But I've been thinking about it...
其实  我也有话想跟你说
Listen, there's more for me to say.
那晚我说的话没经过大脑
I maybe rushed into things. I thought...
等等  你想说什么
Wait a minute. What are you saying?
我想说的是
I'm saying...
我以为我可以为你改变
I thought I could be there for you, Mary Jane...
但是我办不到
...but I can't.
我也在自欺欺人
My mind was playing tricks too.
你到底爱不爱我
Do you love me, or not?
我
I...
不爱
...don't.
你不爱我
You don't.
吻我
Kiss me.
吻你
Kiss you?
我要确定一件事
I need to know something.
只吻一下
Just one kiss.
怎么回事
What's happening?
彼得·帕克
Peter Parker...
跟他的女友
...and the girlfriend.
你要什么
What do you want?
我要你找到蜘蛛人
I want you to find your friend Spider-Man.
叫他下午三点到高塔找我
Tell him to meet me at the Westside Tower at 3:00.
我不知道他在哪里
I don't know where he is.
去找到他
Find him.
不然我就剥了她的皮
Or I'll peel the flesh off her bones.
你敢动她一根寒毛
If you lay one finger on her...
你就怎样
You'll do what?
令郎的未婚妻仍然下落不明
Still no word on the whereabouts of your son's fiancee.
很遗憾
Sorry, Jonah.
都是我的错
It's all my fault.
我把蜘蛛人逼走
I drove Spider-Man away.
只有他能阻止八爪博士
He was the only one who could've stopped Octavius.
对
Yes.
蜘蛛人是个英雄
Spider-Man was a hero.
我只是不肯承认
I just couldn't see it.
他是个
He was a...
小偷  土匪
A thief! A criminal!
（你的好邻居蜘蛛人）
他偷走我的紧身衣  他是全民公敌
He stole my suit! He's a menace to the entire city!
我要告那只臭蜘蛛
I want that wall-crawling arachnid prosecuted!
我要用蜘蛛丝把他吊死
I want him strung up by his web!
我要蜘蛛人
I want Spider-Man!
（他回来了）
她人呢
Where is she?
她不会有事  咱们谈谈
Oh, she'll be just fine. Let's talk.
搞什么
What the hell?
你要拦下那辆列车
You have a train to catch.
救命啊
Help!
刹车失灵  停不下来
Help! Help! I can't stop it! The brakes are gone!
-是蜘蛛人  -天啊  我们死定了
- It's Spider-Man. - Oh, my God, this is it!
叫大家抓紧了
Tell everyone to hang on!
抓紧了
Brace yourselves!
你还有什么妙计
Any more bright ideas?
还有很多
I got a few, yeah!
小心
Whoa, watch out!
慢下来了
We're slowing down.
小心点
Nice and easy, we'll go down.
轻点
Slower. Gently.
他还活着吗
Is he alive?
他只是个
He's...
年轻人
...just a kid.
跟我儿子差不多大
No older than my son.
没事了
It's all right.
我们找到这个
We found something.
我们不会告诉别人
We won't tell nobody.
蜘蛛人  你回来了真好
It's good to have you back, Spider-Man.
他是我的
He's mine!
你得先过我这一关
You want to get to him, you got to go through me.
还有我
And me.
我也是
Me too.
好吧
Very well.
你要我把他放哪儿
Where do you want him?
氚元素呢
And the tritium?
对
Yes.
我要你跟我一样痛不欲生
If only I could cause you the pain that you've caused me.
让我先揭开你的真面目
First we'll see who's behind the mask.
然后看着你痛苦死去
I can look into your eyes as you die.
彼得
Pete.
不
No.
不可能
It can't be.
哈利
Harry.
她人呢  他把她藏在哪儿
Where is she? Where is he keeping her?
-他把玛莉珍抓走了  -他要的是氚元素
- He's got M.J. - No. All he wanted was the tritium.
氚元素
Tritium?
他又要制造核融合机器
He's making the machine again.
到时候纽约市会被他摧毁
When that happens, she'll die, along with half of New York.
-他在哪里  -彼得
- Now, where is he? - Peter...
你杀了我父亲
...you killed my father.
世上有比私人恩怨更重要的事
There are bigger things happening here than me and you.
我一定要阻止他
Harry, please, I've got to stop him.
喂
Hey!
我在跟你讲话
I'm talking to you!
你已经拿到你要的东西  快放了我
You got what you needed for your little science project, now let me go.
不行  你会去报警
I can't let you go, you'd bring the police.
蜘蛛人死了  阻止不了我
Not that anybody could stop me now that Spider-Man's dead.
他没死
He's not dead.
-我才不信  -由不得你不信
- I don't believe you. - Believe it.
惊讶吧
Surprise.
你一松绑
As soon as you get free...
我早该知道  小哈利没种杀你
I should have known Osborn wouldn't have the spine to finish you!
快关掉  否则你会害死更多人
Shut it down, Ock. You're going to hurt a lot more people this time.
我愿意冒这个险
Well, that's a risk we're willing to take.
我可不愿意
Well, I'm not.
抓紧了
Hang on, Mary Jane!
快跑
Run!
这次我看你要怎么逃
Let's see you scurry out of this.
现在怎么办
Now what?
巴博士
Dr. Octavius.
我们一定要把它关掉
We have to shut it down.
告诉我  该怎么把它关掉
Please tell me how.
彼得·帕克
Peter Parker?
聪明的懒惰虫
"Brilliant but lazy."
情况不妙
Look at what's happening.
我们要毁了它
We must destroy it.
我不能毁了它
I can't destroy it.
我故意的
I won't.
你跟我说过聪明才智的道理
You once spoke to me about intelligence.
你说一定要用来造福人类
That it was a gift to be used for the good of mankind.
那是个特权
A privilege.
这些机械手臂把你变成怪物
These things have turned you into something you're not.
别听它们的话
Don't listen to them.
这是我的梦想
It was my dream.
为了伸张正义必须牺牲小我
Sometimes, to do what's right, we have to be steady...
放弃我们最珍爱的东西
...and give up the thing we want the most.
甚至我们的梦想
Even our dreams.
你说的对
You're right.
他说的对
He's right.
听好
Listen.
听我的话
Listen to me now.
告诉我该怎么摧毁它
Now, tell me how to stop it.
太迟了
It can't be stopped.
它坚不可摧
It's self-sustaining now.
-快想办法  -除非
- Think! - Unless...
河水
The river.
用河水把它浇熄
Drown it.
让我来
I'll do it.
不
No!
嗨
Hi.
这真的很重耶
This is really heavy.
玛莉珍
M.J.
万一我们没命
In case we die...
你是爱我的
You do love me.
是的
I do.
虽然你嘴里说不爱
Even though you said you didn't.
我不会以怪物的身份死去
I will not die a monster.
我猜我一直都
I think I always knew...
知道
...all this time...
你真正的身份
...who you really were.
所以我们不能在一起
Then you know why we can't be together.
蜘蛛人永远都有敌人
Spider-Man will always have enemies.
我不能让你冒险
I can't let you take that risk.
我永远
I will...
都会是蜘蛛人
...always be Spider-Man.
你跟我不会有结果
You and I can never be.
玛莉珍
Mary Jane!
有人吗
Hello?
什么人
Who's that?
儿子
Son.
我在这儿
I'm here.
爸
Dad?
-我以为你  -并没有
- I thought you were... - No.
我活在你心中
I'm alive in you, Harry.
现在轮到你了
Now it's your turn.
你发誓要蜘蛛人付出代价
You swore to make Spider-Man pay.
现在让他尝苦头吧
Now make him pay.
彼得是我最好的朋友
But Pete's my best friend.
我是你父亲
And I'm your father.
你太软弱了
You're weak.
你一向都很软弱  除非你真的当家作主
You were always weak. You'll always be weak until you take control.
现在你看到彼得的真面目
Now you know the truth about Peter.
你就要学会坚强
Be strong, Harry.
替我报仇
Avenge me.
-替我报仇雪恨  -不
- Avenge me! - No!
打给黛博拉
All Deborah.
外烩厨子吗
The caterer?
叫她不要打开鱼子酱
Tell her not to open the caviar.
我非这么做不可
Had to do what I had to do.
玛莉珍
Mary Jane.
彼得
Peter.
没有你我活不下去
I can't survive without you.
你不该来的
You shouldn't be here.
我知道你认为  我们不能在一起
I know you think we can't be together.
但是请你让我做自己的决定
But can't you respect me enough to let me make my own decision?
我知道往后会很危险
I know there'll be risks.
但是我要跟你一起面对
But I want to face them with you.
我们不该被拆散
It's wrong that we should only be half-alive...
这是不对的
...half of ourselves.
我爱你
I love you.
我现在站在你的门口
So here I am, standing in your doorway.
我一直都在这儿守候着你
I've always been standing in your doorway.
现在也该有人来救你了
Isn't it about time somebody saved your life?
说话呀
Well, say something.
谢谢你  玛莉珍·华森
Thank you, Mary Jane Watson.
去吧  大英雄
Go get them, tiger.